Guide to the Duke University Police Department Records, 1955-2001 UA.10.03.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Police Department records
1955-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Police Department
UA.10.03.0002
11.75 Linear Feet
The Duke University Police Department provides comprehensive law enforcement and security services to all components of Duke University including the academic campus, a large medical center complex, an 8,000 acre research forest, and a variety of satellite facilities throughout North Carolina. The collection documents the activities and policies of the Police Department. Materials include correspondence, reports, minutes, incident reports, depositions, photographs, the publication Duke Community Safety Report, maps, and other records concerning the operation and activities of the Department. Much of the material relates to parking and traffic problems, complaints, and solutions of the Traffic Committee. Other topics include safety procedures for various campus events and locations including Duke Hospital, internal announcements and administrative matters, and general correspondence. Much of the correspondence is with Paul J. Dumas, director of Duke police from 1971 to 1995. The collection also includes materials pertaining to Duke Police safety measures during basketball championship events, including VHS footage of campus bonfires. The records document the department's commitment to providing a secure and orderly environment for students to learn at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Duke University Police records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in May 1975, July 1980, May 1984, October 1983, March 1995, and July 2014.
Collection Overview
The collection documents the activities and policies of the Police Department. Materials include correspondence, reports, minutes, incident reports, depositions, photographs, the publication Duke Community Safety Report, maps, and other records concerning the operation and activities of the Department. Much of the material relates to parking and traffic problems, complaints, and solutions of the Traffic Committee. Other topics include safety procedures for various campus events and locations including Duke Hospital, internal announcements and administrative matters, and general correspondence. Much of the correspondence is with Paul J. Dumas, director of Duke police from 1971 to 1995. The collection also includes materials pertaining to Duke Police safety measures during basketball championship events, including VHS footage of campus bonfires. The records document the department's commitment to providing a secure and orderly environment for students to learn at Duke University.
Historical note
The role of ensuring law enforcement and safety on Duke’s campus was originally carried out as an extension of facilities management and was a small operation. In 1939 there were only four officers on staff, and by 1961 the force numbered only ten. In the 1960s campus safety was handled by the Traffic and Security office under Physical Plant operations, and gradually increased in size and professionalism. In order to keep up with the needs of an expanding campus and student body, a special committee was appointed by the president to review campus security problems. The committee recommended that security matters should be elevated to the responsibility of the university’s central administration, rather than remain a minor role of maintenance services.
Warren C. A. Bear was hired to the newly created position of Chief of Security Division in 1961, and succeeded by Christopher J. Visas in 1969. In this decade the department hired its first African-American staff members: Timothy Dash, Jr. was hired in 1968 for a brief time, and A. B. Washington was hired in 1969, becoming chief of Public Safety’s campus police division in 1994. Requirements for newly hired patrolmen were formalized, including a minimum of a high school diploma and previous police experience, and additional on-the-job training implemented. The expansion and professionalization of security begun in the 1960s was accelerated in 1971 with the hiring of Paul J. Dumas as Director. Under his leadership the Traffic and Security Office was renamed the Public Safety Department, including police, traffic, and safety divisions and reporting to Business Administration. A detective unit was started and a new zoned campus parking system implemented in 1972 and a year later, in 1973, the first female officer Rosemary Jones joined the staff.
In the 1990s the department continued its efforts to meet the needs of an evolving campus, holding diversity forums and launching community safety initiatives to build rapport with the student body. Paul Dumas was awarded the university's top service award, the University Medal for Distinguished Meritorious Service, being the first university staff member to receive the award as previous recipients were faculty, alumni, or trustees. He retired in 1995, succeeded by Alana Ennis. In 1996, the name of the unit was changed to Duke University Police Department to reflect the fact that many officers had police commissions and equal authority to municipal or county officers, and to avoid confusion with the Occupational and Environmental Safety Office. Clarence Birkhead took control of the Duke University Police Department in 1999, having served with the campus police since 1988. He was followed by Robert Dean from 2005 to 2008, who came out of retirement to serve as director after a four-decade career at Duke. John Dailey took over the role of chief of police in 2009. As of 2014, there were approximately 70 officers on the staff of the Duke University Police Department.
The Traffic Commission was started in 1951 to work in concert with campus security to cope with traffic and parking matters. Membership was composed of staff representatives from various campus units. The Commission had the authority to assess fines and set up judicial boards for appeals.
Health facilities -- United States -- Safety Measures; Campus parking -- North Carolina -- Durham; Traffic safety -- United States; Crowd control; Sports spectators; Duke University. Police Department; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Conduct of life; Duke University -- Basketball; Universities and colleges -- Security measures - United States; Campus police; College students -- Political activity -- United States; Duke University. Police Department; Dumas, Paul J.
- Correspondence Series, 1969-1990; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is divided into two subseries, Departmental and Individual. Departmental correspondence folders are arranged chronologically. Individual correspondence was sent to and from particular staff members, and folders are filed alphabetically by staff member last name.
  - Departmental Correspondence, 1969-1984; 1
    - Departmental correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1974; folder 1 of 3 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1974; folder 2 of 3 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1974; folder 3 of 3 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1975; folder 1 of 3 (Box 1)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1975; folder 2 of 3 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1975; folder 3 of 3 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1976 January - July; folder 1 of 3 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1976 January - July; folder 2 of 3 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1976 January - July; folder 3 of 3 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1976 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 2)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1976 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1977; folder 1 of 4 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1977; folder 2 of 4 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1977; folder 3 of 4 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1977; folder 4 of 4 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1978 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 3)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1978 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1978 July - December; folder 1 of 3 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1978 July - December; folder 2 of 3 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1978 July - December; folder 3 of 3 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1979 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1979 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1979 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 4)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1979 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1980 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1980 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1980 July - December (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1981 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1981 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 5)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1981 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1981 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1982 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1982 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1982 July - December (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1984 January - June (Box 6)
    - Departmental correspondence, 1984 July - December (Box 6)
  - Individual Correspondence, 1969-1990; 2
    - Adams, Jim L. correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Adams, Jim L. correspondence, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Adams, Jim L. correspondence, 1973; folder 1 of 2 (Box 7)
    - Adams, Jim L. correspondence, 1973; folder 2 of 2 (Box 7)
    - Adams, Jim L. correspondence, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1985 January - June (Box 7)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1985 July - December (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1986 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1986 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1986 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1986 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1987 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 8)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1987 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1987 July - December; folder 1 of 3 (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1987 July - December; folder 2 of 3 (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1987 July - December; folder 3 of 3 (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1988 January - June (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1988 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 9)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1988 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1989 January - June; folder 1 of 3 (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1989 January - June; folder 2 of 3 (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1989 January - June; folder 3 of 3 (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1989 July - December (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1990 January - June; folder 1 of 2 (Box 10)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1990 January - June; folder 2 of 2 (Box 11)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1990 July - December; folder 1 of 2 (Box 11)
    - Dumas, Paul J. correspondence, 1990 July - December; folder 2 of 2 (Box 11)
    - Holt, Kenneth M. correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
    - Huestis, Charles B. correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 11)
    - Pleasants, W. W. correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Pye, A. Kenneth correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 11)
    - Schwartz, Michael J. correspondence, 1973, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Steinert, Jeff H. correspondence, 1973 (Box 11)
- Administrative Files Series, 1961-1978; 2
  Administrative Files are organized by subject, and arranged alphabetically.
  - Ambulance Service, 1975-1978 (Box 11)
  - Annual Activity Reports, 1962-1970 (Box 11)
  - Bicycle Policies, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
  - Bulletins, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Bulletins, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Bulletins, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Bulletins, 1977 (Box 12)
  - Confidential Materials, 1972-1974 (Box 12)
  - Endowment Requests, 1972-1975 (Box 12)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1969-1971 (Box 12)
  - Firearms Policy, 1970-1976 (Box 12)
  - Firearms Registration and Storage, 1964-1967 (Box 12)
  - Fire Watch Duty, 1970 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper Articles about Assault Cases, 1972 (Box 12)
  - Personnel Matters, 1972 and undated (Box 13)
  - Relocation of the Department, 1971 (Box 13)
  - Rules and Regulations, 1961 (Box 13)
  - Security Disruption Plans (University Emergency Plans), 1971-1973 (Box 13)
  - Security Policies, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Special Duties, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Student Affairs and Student Leaders, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
  - Surveys, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Testing Procedures for New Applicants, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Training records, 1966-1968 (Box 13)
- Security Series, 1969-2001; 3
  The Security series is organized in three subseries. Hospital Security addresses safety topics at Duke Hospital and files are arranged alphabetically. Events and Campus Locations document police activity to ensure safety at particular times and places on campus; locations are organized alphabetically, followed by specific events. Basketball security addresses the particular measures called for by large crowds on campus to watch and celebrate basketball games, especially the national championship games in the 1990s. This subseries includes video-casettes of public safety footage of university-sponsored bonfires.
  - Hospital Security, 1969-1976; 3
    - Hospital correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
    - Hospital correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
    - Hospital correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 13)
    - Hospital Guard Service, 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Highland Hospital, 1976 (Box 13)
    - Hospital Parking and Towing, 1971-1974 (Box 14)
    - Hospital Security, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Hospital Security Proposals, 1975 (Box 14)
    - Hospital Traffic, 1972-1973 (Box 14)
  - Events and Campus Locations, 1969-1977; 4
    - Army Research Office - Durham (AROD), 1970-1971 (Box 14)
    - Art Museum [Nasher Museum of Art], 1970 (Box 14)
    - Campus Housing, 1971 (Box 14)
    - Perkins Library, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - Perkins Library, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Woman's College, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - Woman's College, 1971 (Box 14)
    - Corporate Executives' Meeting, 1977 October 19 (Box 14)
    - Joe College Weekend, 1971 (Box 14)
    - Rufus Concert in Cameron Indoor Stadium, 1976 (Box 14)
    - President Sanford's Inauguration, 1970 October 17-18 (Box 14)
    - Photographs - Student Strike, 1970 May; folder 1 of 3 (Box 14)
    - Photographs - Student Strike, 1970 May; folder 2 of 3 (Box 14)
    - Photographs - Student Strike, 1970 May; folder 3 of 3 (Box 14)
    - Student Strike, 1970 May 6-7 (Box 14)
    - Prime Minister Trudeau, Commencement Visit, 1974 (Box 14)
    - USA-USSR Games, 1974-1975 (Box 14)
  - Basketball Security, 1972-2001, bulk 1990-2001; 5
    - Basketball, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 14)
    - Basketball, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1991-1992; folder 1 of 2 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1991-1992; folder 2 of 2 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1993-1994 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1994-1997 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1997-1998 (Box 15)
    - Basketball, 1999-2000 (Box 15)
    - Non-Duke Basketball Celebrations, 1993-2001 and undated (Box 15)
    - Celebration Activities at Card Gym Parking Lot, 1991 March 30-31; TRT 00:54:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Security footage of post-game bonfires
    - Post-Game Duke vs. Kansas Activities, 1991 April 1; TRT 00:47:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 2)
      Security footage of pre-game preparations and post-game bonfires
    - NCAA Post-Game Bonfire, 1992 April 4; TRT 00:09:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 3)
    - NCAA Post-Game Bench Burning and Tent City, 1992 April 4; TRT 00:56:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 4)
    - NCAA Post-Game Cameron Gym and Campus, 1992 April 4; TRT 00:36:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 5)
    - IM Lot End of Game and Fire Put Out, 1992 April 6; TRT 00:21:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 6)
    - Public Safety Documentary, copy 1, 1992; TRT 00:21:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 7)
      Documentary describing Duke's history in the NCAA/Final Four games, campus celebrations of increasing intensity and the beginning of the bonfire tradition. Includes clips of televised games and news coverage, police radio recording, security footage, and aggregate incident lists
    - Public Safety Documentary, copy 2, 1992; TRT 00:21:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 8)
    - NCAA, tape 1, 1994 April 2; TRT 01:20:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 9)
    - NCAA, tape 2, 1994 April 2; TRT 00:38:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 10)
      Security footage of Duke police officers' preparations and post-game bonfires
    - NCAA Semi-Final tape 1, copy 1, 1994 April 2; TRT 02:01:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 11)
      Security footage of post-game bonfires; no sound
    - NCAA Semi-Final tape 2, copy 1, 1994 April 2; TRT 00:38:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 12)
    - NCAA Cameron Stadium and Welcome Home, 1994; TRT 01:15:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 13)
      Security footage of pre-game preparations, welcome home ceremony with speeches by President Keohane, basketball players, and Coach Krzyzewski
    - NCAA Semi-Final tape 1, copy 2, 1994 April 2; TRT 02:01:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 14)
    - NCAA Semi-Final tape 2, copy 2, 1994 April 2; TRT 00:38:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 15)
    - Duke/UNC Riot, 1997; TRT 00:56:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 16)
    - Yearlook Tape, undated; TRT 00:40:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 17)
      Security footage of pre-game preparations, post-game bonfires on campus, and speech by Coach Krzyzewski
    - Public Safety Fire Footage, undated; TRT 00:46:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 18)
      Security footage of post-game bonfires on campus
    - WTVD Final Four, 1990-1991; TRT 00:15:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 19)
      Home recording of television news coverage on WTVD of basketball game celebration events and aftermath
    - Game, WTVD, and Post-Game Footage, 1991; TRT 00:38:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 20)
      Basketball game footage of unknown source; bonfire security recordings; WTVD news reporting
    - WRAL interview, copy 1, 1992 April 26; TRT 00:20:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 21)
      Home recording of television news coverage on WRAL of interview conducted by anchor Charlie Gaddy with Duke and NCSU officials about post-basketball game celebrations.
    - WRAL interview, copy 2, 1992 April 26; TRT 00:20:00 (Box 22, Video-cassette 22)
- Transportation Series, 1955-1976; 4
  The Transportation series reflects the perennial challenge of organizing parking and transportation for college campuses. The Traffic Commission subseries begins with history and correspondence, followed by other topics organized alphabetically. The Parking and Traffic subseries begins with correspondence; subject files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Traffic Commission, 1955-1976; 6
    - Traffic Commission History, 1955 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1970; folder 1 of 2 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1970; folder 2 of 2 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1971-1972; folder 1 of 3 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1971-1972; folder 2 of 3 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1971-1972; folder 3 of 3 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972; folder 1 of 5 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972; folder 2 of 5 (Box 16)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972; folder 3 of 5 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972; folder 4 of 5 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972; folder 5 of 5 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission Membership Lists, 1954-1965 (Box 17)
    - Traffic Commission Minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Minutes, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Plans, Proposals and Regulations, 1960-1972 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Report by Clyde Holland, 1965 (Box 18)
    - Parking and Traffic Report by Civil Engineering Department, 1966 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Report from John Green, 1969 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Subcommittee Reports, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Final Report, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Traffic Commission Parking and Traffic Surveys, 1961-1965 and undated (Box 19)
  - Parking and Traffic, 1962-1975; 7
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1968-1972; folder 1 of 3 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1968-1972; folder 2 of 3 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1968-1972; folder 3 of 3 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 19)
    - Parking and Traffic correspondence, 1975 (Box 20)
    - Ad Hoc Parking Committee, 1971 (Box 20)
    - Parking Map Publication, 1972-1975 (Box 20)
    - Parking Maps, 1968-1970 and undated (Box 21)
    - Parking Regulations Brochures, 1960, 1962-1968 (Box 20)
    - Parking Problems and Complaints, 1969-1970; folder 1 of 3 (Box 20)
    - Parking Problems and Complaints, 1969-1970; folder 2 of 3 (Box 20)
    - Parking Problems and Complaints, 1969-1970; folder 3 of 3 (Box 20)
    - Towing, 1973-1975 (Box 20)
    - Zone Parking Plan, 1972 (Box 21)
- Community Safety Reports, 1989-1993; 5
  Published weekly, the Community Safety Reports listed crimes or safety threats reported on Duke's Campus. Reports are arranged in chronological order.
  - Community Safety Reports, 1989 (Box 21)
  - Community Safety Reports, 1990 (Box 21)
  - Community Safety Reports, 1991 (Box 21)
  - Community Safety Reports, 1992 (Box 21)
  - Community Safety Reports, 1993 (Box 21)